Guide to the John Howard Griffin Papers,
Rare Book and Manuscript Library Columbia University Libraries
- Series XIX.The Griffin Journal, 1950-1980
  - Lectures #3, 1966, (1 notebook) (Box 35, Folder 853)
    [A Calendar of Lectures for 1966, running, through May of that year. It provides one a taste of the range of places and settings (as well as fees) Griffin encountered. And there are also notations for some New York visits he had scheduled--with the legendary blues musician Josh White for a photographic session and with his close friend the literary critic Maxwell Geismar.
  - Notebook #4, February & March 1967 (Box 35, Folder 854)
    [Griffin carried along this notebook on his lecture tour to California in February and on to Michigan in March of 1967. His stay in San Francisco includes some somber reflections on visiting an "adults only" bookshop. The end of his circuit in Michigan elicits great relief to be returning home to his wife and children. [A batch of pages was cut from the front of this notebook by Griffin; perhaps these had been unsatisfactory pages of writing or an early draft of a piece later developed on the typewriter.]
  - Notebook #5, 1970 (Box 35, Folder 855)
    [This 1970 notebook accompanied Griffin on one of his most significant trips to Europe, researching for his biography of Thomas Merton. His seventeen year old daughter, Susan, accompanied him on the journey. The first stop was Amsterdam, on January 27, 1970, pronouncing himself "more at home here than anywhere in the states." It was a city that his close friend, pianist Robert Casadesus often performed, especially at the Concertgebow, where Griffin attended an all-Beethoven concert by pianist Annie Fischer. He took the opportunity to photograph this great musician in performance, and visited with her afterward... pronounced the recital "a real glory--one of the finest concerts I ever heard. Like Lipatti and Schnabel combined". The next morning he visited the Rijks Museum, "seeing the Rembrandts, Vermeers, etc. Tremendous. To the Van Gogh Museum this afternoon." After three days in Amsterdam, he spent three days in Brussels, staying with the psychiatrist and Merton enthusiast Dr. Vander-Elst. On February 2nd, he took the train to Strasbourg and was met by his old friends, Antoinette and Alexander Grunelius. These great friends of the Maritains drove Griffin and his daughter to their Chateau at Kolbsheim (the repository of the papers of Jacques and Raissa Maritain), where they stayed a few days.. Griffin then spent five days with Jacques Maritain in Toulouse, where the 87 year old philosopher had a tiny hermitage on the grounds where the motherhouse of the Little Brothers and Sisters Order is located. Many passaqes here about Maritain, several of the sisters who did his secretarial work (Sister Marie Pascale, in particular, who typed the philosopher's manuscripts and letters--her signature is under many of Maritain's letters on file at HRC), as well as several interesting cooking experiences with Sister Marie Emmanuel.. A week later, Griffin made several trips to Prades (Merton's birthplace), Montaubin and St. Antonin (where Merton lived as a child), and on to Paris, photographing and notetaking all the way. On February 14, he visited with the daughter of Leon Bloy, the French writer and thinker who was instrumental in converting the Maritains to Catholicism, after a search of several days. Part of this experience, though not mentioned in this notebook, laid the groundwork for his last piece of fiction--the humorous take-off upon hearing the sweet sound of a sackbutt (Pilgrimage, Latitudes Press, 1985).
  - Notebook #6, 1974 (Box 35, Folder 856)
    [Lecture notes for a series on "Dominant Institutions" given during a two-week period at Loretto Heights University in Denver, Colorado. Griffin went to Loretto Heights for two weeks every year during the 1970s to lecture, teach classes and conduct seminars on various aspects of society: racism, injustice, freedom, spirituality--and how the person is thus affected by these realities. In this comfortable academic setting, he was able to develop a deeper set of ideas than one three hour lecture at a university or church could provide--especially when he was in another city by the next day. He enjoyed these times at Loretto Heights, a Catholic institution known for its progressive system which was influenced by Sister Mary Luke Tobin, a close associate of both Merton and Griffin over the years. He utilized this annual visit to Denver to develop his ongoing lectures more deeply, benefitting from the learned response of some of the faculty, as well as a pool of intelligent Catholic students, including many from foreign countries. His daughter Susan was a student at Loretto Heights and her tuition was given in exchange for Griffin's annual appearances.. The lecture notes themselves will give the scholar a clear idea of the way in which Griffin built up the background for his lectures--scholarly research to give context to speeches that were always based on personal experience and more often than not about his Black Like Me and subsequent civil rights work.. Here the background is separated out from the foreground; the objective set apart from the subjective while his speeches integrate both realms.
  - Notebook #7, 1976 (Box 35, Folder 857)
    [Records two days of solitude at Bemidji, Minnesota on a lake surrounded by woods. He was at the time teaching writing at The Upper Midwest Writing Conference [see Series XVII for related information and correspondence]. Griffin simply records the solitary time and does not mention the conference at all. He records the birdcalls, describes the lake and woods, remarks about being awake at dawn--and then compares his sense of unity there as reminiscent of his time at Merton's hermitage four years earlier, July 1976.. The second section finds Griffin recuperating from several heart attacks after a month long tour from October 20 to November 20 (mostly in Canada). That tour ended in Rochester, New York where he was barely able to make his appearance. Returning to Fort Worth, he kept his Journal in this notebook on a bed desk his wife had purchased, because he was unable to work on his studio typewriter. Very ill, he convinced the doctor to let him remain at home instead of going to the hospital. Slowly, he begins to improve in the warm context of his family--wife and younger daughter (Amanda), as well as his mother (Lena Griffin), all helping and staying watch. Each day he received communion from his close friend, Father George Curtsinger (photographer, pianist, writer; books published by Latitudes). November 27 to December 3, 1976.
  - Notebook #8, Toronto, June 11-20, 1977 (Box 36, Folder 858)
    [The first section includes Griffin's extensive notes on writing and art in outline form and is clearly influenced by Maritain's aesthetic works. He begins with his view of writing that "creative writing cannot be taught, but we can learn to remove many of the impediments to creativity". Discussion of various elements: characterization, writer as creative filter, challenge to express the inexpressible, universality of experience ("you have to become all men at all times: leave yourself and become the other. Gamble on truth"). How keeping a journal can aid in these ventures: "This means that sometimes, for the sake of truth, you have to write things that are personally offensive to you .... This comes most most naturally from keeping an absolutely private journal." Then there is a section entitled "Essences and Accidentals" which is a five page outline of Maritain's ideas from Creative Intuition in Art and Poetry (Griffin's aesthetic Bible). Finally, some Griffin notes on techniques, revision, things to avoid and misplaced motivations. [included herein is a folder containing one stray sheet of notes in Griffin's hand, plus a three-page carbon typescript he made from Maritain's Creative Intuition, ("definitions of art").]. The remainder of this notebook is as profound in the personal sense as the first portion is in the artistic sense. Griffin arrived in Toronto on June 11, 1977. He was met at the airport by Dr. Viktor Frankel, a thinker Griffin had long admired and was meeting for the first time. Frankel is best known for his first book, Man's Search for Meaning. His account of enduring a Nazi concentration camp and the existential opus that begins his psychoanalytical career as the founder of logotherapy. The next day, Griffin had a long dialogue with Frankel which he called, ..a great interview. I have never in my life met a man whose thoughts and conclusions so nearly matched my own." Griffin discusses Frankel's ideas at great length and their affinity to his own, less systematic worldview.. Also at great length, Griffin discusses his depleted physical energy due to diabetes and heart-related ailments. "My problem, my physical condition obliges me to make demands on others that go against my conscience. When others through love and perception sense the needs and volunteer the aid, then the conflict ceases and is replaced by an overwhelming gratitude. It has always been profoundly repellant to me to have to ask someone for what must be given. That is the great dissonance of my life: My needs, for example, deprive my wife, Tom [Father Tom McKillop], even my children, of the peace and rest they need...no matter how willing they are to help. Because I try to hold off asking until too late, I face them with crises and fatigue. This destroys me and worsens the condition. I hold off asking (imposing) until I then grow sick and cry out for help.". In rereading the "Scattered Shadows" chapters in The Reader, Griffin was deeply struck by the attitude (of false heroism) he had while slowly losing his sight in France thirty years earlier, in 1946. But he recognized the falsity then and overcame his own hypocrisy. "Strange indeed--my present helplessness and confusion wiped from memory the very meaning of that earlier discovery. There I could find finally objective meaning--the fragments were finally perceived as a whole. This time [with one leg amputated, with regular heart failures, constant pain and insomnia] I have been unable to do that--so meaning is too often replaced by sadness, even despair, even blackness without light but I cannot feel it too often Too often everything, even knowledge and perception seem wiped out by the heart-organ's physical inability to function--so the symbolic and real heart get clouded, desperate, fragmented, unwhole--and I know and hate-it-and beg for help.... Dr. Frankel refreshed these dim memories that have so permeated all my work."
  - Notebook #9, June 4-7, 1978 (Box 36, Folder 859)
    [This is Griffin's final travel notebook, recording a visit he made to the Toronto home of Father Tom McKillop, his closest friend and spiritual advisor in the final few years. The entries reflect the desperate state of Griffin's health. Any intention of lecturing or doing interviews was cancelled. He simply spent time with his friend, made his confession, and received communion each day as they said the Mass together. Despite all the discomfort, Griffin felt "great joy to be back in this peaceful house, in the safety and security of friendship".
  - Notebook #10, January-24 May 1980 (Box 36, Folder 860)
    [This final notebook postdates the last entry in his typewritten journal, which itself runs only 13 single spaced typed pages, from January until May 24, 1980 (and ending on page 2762).. From that last typed passage until the first entry in this final autograph notebook, a full month had passed without any writing.. Then, on June 23 until July 17 of 1980, he scrawled his last fifteen pages in this notebook. In addition, there are three handwritten pages toward the back of the notebook: this is a preliminary draft for an article commissioned by Litton magazines, concerning his views on changing skin color. The draft is unquestionably the very last piece Griffin wrote other than these fifteen pages that end his overall Journal.. The piece on skin color was finished in typescript (no carbon remains and perhaps he did not make one) for a June 17 deadline which he met and for which he collected a check from Litton for what would be his last published writing to appear in his lifetime
- Series XX. Posthumous Papers
  John Howard Griffin left his home the afternoon of July 21, 1980. He was checked into Medical Plaza Hospital by his long-time physician, Dr. E. Ross Kyger. Griffin lived another fifty days, expiring of a cerebral hemorrhage on September 9, 1980. He was less than three months into his sixtieth year. The funeral was held on September 11, and Griffin was buried at the Mansfield Cemetery, Mansfield, Texas, next to the grave of his old friend, Clyde Parker Holland (father of Griffin's widow, Elizabeth). He was survived by his wife, four children, his mother, brother, and two sisters.. Griffin's funeral was attended by hundreds of friends, family members, and devoted acquaintances. The Mass was written by Father Tom McKillop--a moving ceremony that included many of Griffin's words read and anecdotes remembered. Friends travelled from all over the United States and Canada to attend. A fuller version of that day is detailed in Fr.McKillop's text, in many news features and obituaries
  - Tom McKillop Funeral Mass of John Howard Griffin, [Mansfield, TX], [Sept. 1980], (8 page t.ms. (photocopy) (Box 36, Folder 861)
  - WAY magazine Special Edition devoted to John Howard Griffin, San Francisco, CA, September 1981, (64 pages) (Box 36, Folder 862)
    [Includes articles by Robert Ellsberg, Irving Sussman, Joe Noonan, and Cornelia Jessey
  - Daniel, Bradford "The Intrinsic Other: The Life and Work of John Howard Griffin." Outline for a film documentary, [n.p.], 1980, (5 page t.ms.) (Box 36, Folder 863)
  - Daniel, Bradford To Elizabeth Griffin, [n.p.], 14 October 1980, (1 page a.l.s.) (Box 36, Folder 863)
  - Miller, Keith D. "Courageous Witness", Fellowship: Nyack, NY, March 1981, (4 page photocopy) (Box 36, Folder 864)
  - Ellsberg, Robert Article on John Howard Griffin in Cloud of Witness and Sojourners, [n.p.], 1981 & 1991, (12 page photocopy) (Box 36, Folder 865)
  - Sharp, Ernest "The Man Who Changed His Skin", American Heritage, 1989, (14 page photocopy) (Box 36, Folder 866)
  - The First Annual John Howard Griffin Festival of the Arts I, St. Joseph's College, Toronto, 28 October 1983, (5 program and flyers) (Box 36, Folder 867)
    [The first festival was organized by Father Tom McKillop and sponsored by the Youth Corps of Toronto; performers included actors Michael Kramer and Jimmy Pappas, performing a scene from Scattered Shadows; musical performances by pianist Luiz de Moura Castro, Clarinetist Bridget de Moura Castro, and sopranos Caudettte LeBlanc; plus readings of Griffin's work by Elizabeth Griffin and Robert Bonazzi
  - John Howard Griffin Festival of the Arts. Second and Third, Fort Worth, TX, 1984 & 1985, (2 programs, 1 invitation) (Box 36, Folder 868)
  - Pilgrimage, Latitudes Press: Mansfield, TX, 1985, (12 page booklet) (Box 36, Folder 869)
    [Commemorative edition of the Third Annual John Howard Griffin Festival. Limited edition, 500 copies.
  - Certificates of death, Fort Worth, 1980, (2 page photocopies) (Box 36, Folder 870)
    [On one of his last days in the hospital, John Howard Griffin said to father McKillop: "It's so hard to be reduced to nothing! All of I have left now is the pure silence of love." And that was everything.
- Series XXI. Photographs
  - Animals -- cat, rabbit & cat; deer, (3 photographs) (Box 36, Folder 871)
  - Belgium, (10 photographs) (Box 36, Folder 872)
  - Luis Berber, [n.p.], August 1965, (1 photograph) (Box 36, Folder 873)
  - Blacks in Mississippi, Mississippi, August 1974, (9 photographs) (Box 36, Folder 874)
  - Lola Bobesco, Susanne Genty and Jacques Genty, Huy, Belgium, December 1965, (2 photographs) (Box 36, Folder 875)
  - Lorenzo Bonazzi, [n.p.], 9 June 1967, (1 photograph) (Box 36, Folder 876)
  - Children playing, [n.p.], 12 July 1962, (1 photograph) (Box 36, Folder 877)
  - [Father Clayton?] Portrait, Fort Worth, texas, 1974, (1 photograph) (Box 36, Folder 877A)
  - Earl Coverdale, Spirit Lake, Iowa, June 1964, (1 photograph) (Box 36, Folder 878)
  - Meade Crane, Texas, 4 June 1967, (1 photograph) (Box 36, Folder 879)
  - Andrew Dasberg & Robert Ellis, Taos, New Mexico, 1964, (2 photographs) (Box 36, Folder 880)
  - Andrew Dasberg, Taos, New Mexico, 1964/65, (2 photographs) (Box 36, Folder 881)
  - Madame Suzanne Dessertennes, [n.p.] & Denver, 1974, (2 photographs) (Box 36, Folder 882)
  - Father Godfrey Diekmann, [n.p.], August 1965, (2 photographs) (Box 36, Folder 883)
  - Catherine de Hueck Doherty, Combermere, Ontario, 1968, (2 photographs) (Box 36, Folder 884)
  - Nell Dorr, [n.p.], December 1972, (1 photograph) (Box 36, Folder 885)
  - Michael Dunne, [n.p.], 2 November 1974, (1 photograph) (Box 36, Folder 886)
  - P.D. East, [n.p.], 1962, (1 photograph) (Box 36, Folder 887)
  - Brother Emmanuel, Detroit, 1964, (1 photograph) (Box 36, Folder 888)
  - Sister Fleurette, IMS, Los Angeles, CA, 1 July 1964, (1 photograph) (Box 36, Folder 889)
  - Flowers, [n.p.], May 1965, (1 photograph) (Box 36, Folder 890)
  - France, 1960s & 1970s, (4 photograph) (Box 36, Folder 891)
  - Anne Freemantle, New York and Texas, 1965-1975, (3 photograph) (Box 36, Folder 892)
  - George Galinkin, Mansfield, Texas, 1972, (1 photograph) (Box 36, Folder 893)
  - Maxwell Geismar, [n.p.], 8 June 1962, (1 photograph) (Box 36, Folder 894)
  - Ernesto Tovar, Mexico, 1961, (1 photograph) (Box 36, Folder 894)
  - Maxell Geismar, [n.p.], 1965, (1 photograph) (Box 36, Folder 895)
  - Father George Amanda Griffith's communion mass, [Mansfield, Texas], 1972, (1 photograph) (Box 36, Folder 896)
  - Father Mottet Amanda Griffith's communion mass, [Mansfield, Texas], 1972, (2 photographs) (Box 36, Folder 896)
  - Amanda Griffin, [Mansfield, Texas], 1966-1972, (26 photographs) (Box 36, Folder 897)
  - Gregory Griffin, [v.p.], 1961-1965, (12 photographs) (Box 36, Folder 898-902)
  - John Howard Griffin Getting haircut, [v.p.], 1974, (3 photographs) (Box 36, Folder 903)
  - John Howard Griffin On various t.v. shows, [Mansfield, Texas], October 1974, (2 photographs) (Box 36, Folder 904)
  - John Howard Griffin Humorous mock-entry on Who's Who re sackbut player, [Mansfield, Texas], 1973 & 1975, (2 photographs) (Box 36, Folder 905)
  - John Howard Griffin & Dick Gregory, [n.p.], 1973, (1 photograph) (Box 36, Folder 906)
  - John Howard Griffin At Merton's hermitage, [n.p.], 1973, (1 photograph) (Box 36, Folder 907)
  - John Howard Griffin Taken by Father George, [n.p.], [1967], (1 photograph) (Box 36, Folder 908)
  - John Howard Griffin & Antoinette Grunelius Working together on the Gwen John project, Kolbshein, France, [1967], (6 photographs) (Box 36, Folder 909)
  - Chateau and chapel, Kolbshein, France, [1967], (2 photographs) (Box 36, Folder 909)
  - John Howard Griffin & Msgr. Brady, Windsor, Ontario, March 1966, (1 photograph) (Box 36, Folder 910)
  - John Howard Griffin At Pacem in Terris Award, Windsor, Ontario, 1968, (1 photograph) (Box 37, Folder 911)
  - Griffin family (Piedy; Mother; Susan; George; Amanda; and John Howard) in groups, [Mansfield, Texas], 1963-1966, (10 photographs) (Box 37, Folder 912 & 913)
  - Lena Mae Griffin Griffin's mother, [Mansfield, Texas], 1964, (2 photographs) (Box 37, Folder 914 & 915)
  - Piedy Griffin Griffin's wife, [Mansfield, Texas], 1966/1967, (2 photographs) (Box 37, Folder 916)
  - Susan Griffin Griffin's daughter, [Mansfield, Texas], 1967, (1 photograph) (Box 37, Folder 916)
  - Susan Griffin Griffin's daughter, [Mansfield, Texas], 1960s and 1970s, (13 photographs) (Box 37, Folder 917-920)
  - Dom Bede Griffiths Born December 17, 1906, in Walton on Thames, England; died May 13, 1993, at the small monastic ashram he had headed since 1968, in Tamil Nadu, India. Griffiths' worked to foster ecumenical relations between Christians and Hindus in India. He assisted in the foundation of Kurisumala Ashram, a monastery of the Syrian Rite of the Catholic Church which uses the Syriac language in its prayers and services. Griffiths wore the `kavi' (saffron-coloured) dress of the sannyasi (monk) and used Sanskrit and other Indian languages in the celebration of the Christian liturgy combined with the study of the mystical tradition of Hinduism., [Mansfield, Texas], 1963/1964, (4 photographs) (Box 37, Folder 921-924)
  - House, interior, [Mansfield, Texas], 1966, (7 photographs) (Box 37, Folder 925)
  - Penn Jones Portrait, [Mansfield, Texas], July 1963, (1 photograph) (Box 37, Folder 926)
  - Lili Kraus (with Piedy and John Howard Griffin) Snapshots, [v.p.], 1970s, (4 photographs) (Box 37, Folder 927)
  - Halldor Laxness & Corneille Heymans Nobel prizewinners in literature and medicine, Huy, belgium, December 1965, (1 photograph) (Box 37, Folder 928)
  - Denis Levertov Portrait, [n.p.], [1975], (1 photograph) (Box 37, Folder 929)
  - Jacques Maritain Portrait and snapshots, [v.p.], 1964-1967, (4 photographs) (Box 37, Folder 930)
  - Jacques Maritain et al With Thomas Merton, Father Sullivan and John Howard Griffin, [v.p.], 1966, (6 photographs) (Box 37, Folder 931)
  - Thomas Merton In hermitage, Trappist, KY, [n.d.], (1 photograph) (Box 37, Folder 932)
  - Merton's hermitage and environment, Trappist, KY, 1972, (6 photographs) (Box 37, Folder 933)
  - Thomas Merton With camera in rail yard, KY, 1968, (5 photographs) (Box 37, Folder 934)
  - Thomas Merton Portrait, KY, 25 April 1968, (1 photograph) (Box 37, Folder 935)
  - Thomas Merton Reading, KY, 19 March 1963, (1 photograph) (Box 37, Folder 936)
  - Thomas Merton Official portrait by John Howard Griffin, KY, 20 March 1963, (1 photograph) (Box 37, Folder 937)
  - Thomas Merton At the hermitage with John Howard Griffin, KY, 1967, (2 photographs) (Box 37, Folder 938)
  - Mexican Joe's living room, [n.p.], February 1968, (1 photograph) (Box 37, Folder 939)
  - Mexico scenery (Santa Maria and Rancho Santo Domingo), [n.p.], 1965 & 1975, (5 photographs) (Box 37, Folder 940)
  - Milhaud Trio, Fort Worth, Texas, 8 September 1973, (1 photograph) (Box 37, Folder 941)
  - Monestary of Gethsemani, Trappist, KY, 24 January 1963, (1 photograph) (Box 37, Folder 942)
  - Father Stanley Murphy Portrait, [n.p.], 29 July 1962, (1 photograph) (Box 37, Folder 943)
  - Father Stanley Murphy Celebrating mass in studio of John Howard Griffin, Mansfield, Texas, 11 July 1966, (1 photograph) (Box 37, Folder 944)
  - Zara Nelsova Zara Nelsova was born in Winnipeg in 1918. Her parents had emigrated from Russia in 1910. Zara made her solo orchestral debut, playing the Lalo Concerto with the London Symphony Orchestra under Malcolm Sargent. After the war Nelsova was able to realize her lifelong ambition of studying with Pablo Casals. In 1955, Nelsova gave a landmark series of recitals for solo cello in London and New York and in 1966, she became the first North American cellist to tour the Soviet Union. Zara was the favorite cellist of Ernest Bloch, who wrote three Solo Suites for her and presided as conductor for her recording of his Schelomo. Samuel Barber also chose her as soloist for a recording of his Cello Concerto, with him conducting. She died in 1995., Minneapolis, 12 March 1963, (7 photographs) (Box 37, Folder 945)
  - Philip Noel-Baker, Dominique Pire, Professor C. Heymans, and H. Laxness Four Nobel Prize Winners, Huy, Belgium, December 1965, (1 photograph) (Box 37, Folder 946)
  - The Novice, Morelia, Michoacan, Mexico, 1961, (1 photograph) (Box 37, Folder 947)
  - Rabbi Joel Orent Portrait, [n.p.], September 1969, (1 photograph) (Box 37, Folder 948)
  - Charles Rector Portrait, [n.p.], 25 March 1968, (1 photograph) (Box 37, Folder 949)